Guide to the Albert J. Guérard's Research Materials on John Hawkes, 1959-1994
Department of Special Collections
Albert J. Guérard's Research Materials on John Hawkes,
1959-1994
Special Collections M0898
Guérard, Albert J (Albert Joseph), 1914-
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biography
Albert Joseph Guérard (1914- ) is an emeritus professor of English at Stanford University and a novelist. John Hawkes (1925- ), a former student of Guérard's in his advanced writing class at Harvard, 1947-49, is a professor of literature at Brown University. John Hawkes and his wife Sophie are friends of Albert and Maclin Guérard. Guérard notes that "Although John Hakes is not a household name in the world of commercial best sellers, he has a very high literary reputation in the United States and in France, where he has been called the heir of Faulkner. I regard him, together with Gil Sorrentino, as the most important avant-garde novelist writing in English and possibly the best stylist of any novelist writing in English."
Scope and Content
The Albert J. Guérard Research Materials on John Hawkes consists of 1.5 manuscript boxes. The collection contains 19 letters and the photocopies of over 200 letters written by Hawkes to Albert and Maclin Guérard between 1959 and 1994. The originals of the photocopied letters are held by the Harvard Libraries. Also included are several folders of original letters from Sophie Hawkes, primarily to Maclin Guérard. The collection also contains 6 folders of John Hawkes' scholarly works, including page proofs, rare periodical publications, and a copy of The VOICE PROJECT.
Access Terms
Hawkes, John, 1925-; Hawkes, Sophie.; American literature--20th century.; Authors, American.; America--Intellectual life--20th century.; Authors.; Phonotapes.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. John Hawkes Reading at Stanford. Phonodisc.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. Voice Project.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. Travesty.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. Adventures in the Alaskan Skin Trade.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. Second Skin.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. "Notes on Violence."; Hawkes, John, 1925-. "Peau neuve."; Hawkes, John, 1925-. The Blood Oranges.; Hawkes, John, 1925-. "The Nearest Cemetery."; The Personal Voice; a contemporary prose reader, edited by Albert J. Guérard et. al.
Container List
All quotations are taken from Albert Guerard's notes about the collection.
- "Photocopies of 201 letters, many of them long, written by John Hawkes (JH) to Albert and Maclin Guerard (AJG and MG) between 1959 and 1994.
  These letters rank with the best by a 20th century novelist." The originals are held by the Harvard Libraries.
  - 83 photocopies of letters written by JH to AJG. 1959-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 118 photocopies of letters written by JH to AJG and MG. 1968-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes on the letters in folders 1 & 2 identifying people and situations alluded to by JH in the letters. Prepared under AJG's direction. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 19 letters, several of them long, or card/letters from JH to AJG or MG. 1958-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "The eloquent third paragraph of the May 16, 1968 letter from Greece should be compared with the extraordinary improvisation on Lesbos in John Hawkes Reading at Stanford (Stanford Recordings in Sound). My printout of the improvisation is enclosed with the May 16 letter. But the wonderful play of the voice needsto be heard. Also, a photocopy of a letter to Mark Spilka,head of the English Department, urging tenure for a colleague, Claire Rosenfield."
- Original letters from Sophie Hawkes, primarily to MG. "These letters would be of great value to a biographer since they give a good sense of their daily lives, particularly while living and working in France."
  - 16 letters from SH to MG 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 9 letters from SH to MG 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 10 letters from SH to MG 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 13 letters from SH to MG 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 14 letters from SH to MG 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 10 letters from SH to MG 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 12 letters from SH to MG, undated. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Photocopies of many corrections and cuts made by John Hawkes on the page proof of Adventures in the Alaskan Skin Trade. n.d., 18 pages. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    This is the most traditional or 'mainstream' of Hawkes' novels, and some notes suggest a concern for conventional ordering."
  - - JH's text of a 5-page talk on the relationship of poetry to experimental fiction, given to a large audience (over 400) of AJG's Harvard course Comp. Lit. 166, "Forms of the Modern Novel." 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "A subtle, packed gem that had the students baffled."
  - - Copy of a memorial statement written by JH on Aristedes Stavrolakes. A former student and friend of AJG who committed suicide. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "Elsewhere Hawkes mentions the suicide as one of the events or forces that went into his novel Second Skin.
  - - 15 page text of a "Conversation with John Hawkes," June 7, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "The interviewer Salwa Karoui asks brief questions, with more than 95% of the text consisting of Hawkes' monologues. I don't know whether this recent interview has been published anywhere."
  - Full copy of the uncorrected proof for JH's Travesty. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 4 rare JH periodical publications
  - -"Notes on Violence," in Audience (Spring, 1960), 1960, p. 60. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    "Hawkes' first published critical statement, noting on relation of contemporary poetry and experimental fiction. Issue also contains my (AJG) introduction to the "Cambridge Anti-Realists."
  - - "Peau neuve," in Les Lettres Nouvelles 1967 (octobre-novembre 1967). (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Translation of the first chapter of Second Skin.
  - - "Burnt Orange" in The Dutton Review 1 (1970), 1970, p. 137-50. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "Selection from The Blood Oranges.
  - - "The Nearest Cemetery," in San Francisco Review Annual 1 (1963), p.178-185. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "Pages from draft of Second Skin, differing importantly from the published novel. See Carol Hryciw, John Hawkes: An Annotated Bibliography, p. 27 for reprinting"
- VOICE PROJECT/An Experiment in Teaching Writing to College Freshmen. (U. S. Office of Education, Bureau of Research Report, 1967), xi-xxxix, 3-305. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  "This project, directed by Hawkes under my general supervision as Co-Director of Freshman English, involved 100 Stanford freshmen and eight visiting writers who devoted their entire time to teaching one experimental section throughout the year. The report, with a history of the project and a summary of its methods and findings signed by Hawkes, is on xi-xxxix. The greatest educational value (and value for the biographer) lies in the detailed printed record of taped sample classes, with Hawkes' voice in exchanges identified by 'Jack.' The Voice Project and the freshman English anthology The Personal Voice: A Contemporary Prose Reader co-edited by Albert Guerard, John Hawkes, Maclin Guerard, Claire Rosenfield (Lippincott, 1964) were early and probably influential examinations of the concept of authorial voice that would later become current, with the word voice used in a number of later anthologies and repeatedly used in literary criticism."